COTSEN4 COTSEN4
Cotsen Children's Library
- Penelope Farmer, 1971 - 1985
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1985
    General correspondence between Farmer and McElderry, and between McElderry and others, especially her agent Deborah Owen, regarding Farmer's work. Professional correspondence regards several of Penelope's projects ultimately not taken on by Atheneum, including The Story of Persephone (Collins, 1972), a collection of Farmer's poems (1974), and Coal Train (William Heinemann, 1977). Other professional correspondence includes discussion of a promotional booklet about Farmer published by Atheneum in winter 1972, an October 1976 article about Farmer in Horn Book Magazine, and the unauthorized use of lines from Farmer's 1969 novel Charlotte Sometimes in a song by The Cure. McElderry and Farmer discuss three of Farmer's visits to the US: a fall 1972 visit to New York; a summer 1973 tour sponsored by Atheneum, including appearances at the Intermountain conference in Utah and the Loughborough conference in Towson, MD, publicity tours of the southwest and California, and Labor Day weekend with McEdlerry and her husband on Nantucket; and a summer 1975 visit to New York accompanied by her husband Michael Mockridge and their children. Personal correspondence includes discussion of Farmer's separation from Mockridge in 1974, several letters from McElderry to Mockridge, Farmer's illness in spring 1980, the publication of Farmer's first adult novel in 1984, and her remarriage.
  - Beginnings: Creation Myths of the World, 1978
    Folder contains primarily correspondence with/regarding the following individuals: Penelope Farmer, Antonio & Nono Frasconi, Jane Birkett of Chatto & Windus (copublishers), Judy Long, and Deborah Owen, Farmer's agent. Farmer compiled and edited these creation myths from around the world, and Antonio Frasconi illustrated them with original woodcuts. Professional topics discussed include the difficulties of coproduction, obtaining rights for the myths used, line edits to the manuscript, format and design, advertising posters, and reviews and responses to the book. Farmer dedicated the book to McEdlerry. Farmer began both Beginnings and Year King around the same time; some of the early correspondence discusses both books ( Year King is often referred to as "the twin book"). McElderry and Birkett also discuss Farmer's William and Mary and projects by Susan Cooper, another author published jointly by both houses. Personal topics include several of Farmer's visits to the US, her divorce, and the death of McElderry's husband.
  - Castle of Bone, 1972
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Farmer, Farmer's agent Debbie Owen, and Jane Birkett at Chatto & Windus, which copublished the book, regarding this mystery novel. Castle was Farmer's first book with Atheneum; early correspondence discusses the possibility of Harcourt Brace Jovanovich releasing Farmer from her contract. Other topics include general editorial suggestions (e.g. the ages of the characters, shortening Farmer's long sentences, and the novel's conclusion) and line edits, as well as discussion about whether Atheneum would use the English jacket, transatlantic differences in spelling and punctuation, design and printing concerns, and promotion and reviews of the novel. McElderry and Farmer discuss McElderry's visit to England in the spring of 1972, and Farmer's October 1972 visit to New York, including a promotional cocktail party at the Cosmopolitan Club. There are also Christmas letters from Farmer's children to McElderry. The file contains a letter from Ursula Le Guin with her thoughts on Castle and her involvement in a public controversy she calls "the Road Dahl affair;" there is also a signed letter from the actress Joanne Woodward explaining the appearance of Castle in her film Summer Wishes, Winter Dreams. Correspondence between Birkett and McElderry includes discussion of Susan Cooper's work.
  - Correspondence regarding Elementary English article, 1974
    Correspondence regarding an article McElderry wrote about Farmer's work and the editorial process for the September 1974 issue of the journal Elementary English. File includes a cassette recording of a conversation between McElderry and Farmer during Farmer's 1973 visit to McElderry's home on Nantucket, a transcription of the tape, letters from John Donovan, director of the Children's Book Council, a draft of the article, an edited copy of the article, and correspondence between Farmer, Farmer's agent Deborah Owen, and Donovan regarding who holds the rights to the published article.
  - William and Mary, 1974
    Correspondence between McElderry, Farmer, Jane Birkett at Chatto & Windus, and Farmer's agent Deborah Owen, regarding this novel about a pair of friends and their magical sea shell. Topics of correspondence include general editorial notes, line edits, the difficulties of co-editing with Birkett, jacket illustration by Antony Maitland, attribution of a poem briefly excerpted in the novel, reviews and further interest, and finally the remaindering of the book in 1983. McElderry and Birkett also discuss Susan Cooper's work.
  - Year King, 1977; Chronological
    Correspondence between McElderry, Farmer, Farmer's agent Deborah Owen, and Jane Birkett at Chatto & Windus, which copublished this book about the complicated relationship between a set of twins (often referred to in early correspondence as "the twin book"). McElderry did much general editing of the manuscript: topics include concerns about length, the lack of resolution, and whether the book should be published as an adult or YA novel. There is also a 54 page letter of line edits suggested by McElderry, along with a second copy of the letter with Farmer's handwritten comments. Other topics of correspondence include William Byrd's jacket, printing and design concerns, permissions for quotes, and reviews. Discussion of Beginnings and McElderry's article about Farmer in Elementary English are interwoven throughout the correspondence, as is discussion between McEdlerry and Birkett regarding Susan Cooper's work, especially Silver on the Tree. Personal correspondence between McElderry and Farmer discusses Farmer's poetry, William Rayner's book Big Mister, elections in both the US and UK, and Farmer's spring 1977 trip to Israel. The final letter informs Farmer of the reversion of rights to her for Year King, William and Mary and Castle of Bone (1985).
- James Flora, 1980
  - Wanda and the Bumbly Wizard
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Flora and Judy Long regarding this humurous adventure story written and illustrated by Flora. Topics of correspondence include line edits, reviews of Flora's previous book Grandpa's Ghost Stories, whether Flora would represent Atheneum at the "New York is Book Country" street fair, interest in Wanda from Metheun in England, and a request for advice from Flora regarding his daughter Roussie's writing career.
- Antonio Frasconi
  - General Correspondence
    Correspondence mainly between Frasconi, McElderry, and Frasconi's wife Nono, regarding a number of Frasconi's projects.
    correspondence with Pura Belpre White, arranging for her to meet Frasconi; Frasconi illustrating White's collection of Puerto Rican tales? letters to G.C. Alberghini, secretary general of the Children's Book Fair in Bologna; Frasconi asked to be part of 7th exhibition for illustrators Dorothy Crispo's "Estevanico -- Negro Discoverer of the Southwest" - reffered to MKM by Frasconi Susan Manchester's Marine Bestiary or Sea Circus son Miguel - asking MKM to be a reference for conscientious objector status; and to Pablo about his films at the Esther Bear Gallery in Santa Barbara Mae Durham Roger, film about Frasconi other exhibits of his work at La Casa del Libro in San Juan, the Cayman Gallery, Terry Dintenfass Inc (NYC) letters of recommendation for Guggenheim fellowship and reappointment at SUNY Purchase
- Antonio Frasconi and Doris Dana, 1972
  - Crickets and Frogs, 1972
    Correspondence between McElderry, Fransconi, Dana, and Dana's agent Joan Daves regarding this bilingual version of Gabriela Mistral's story Grillos y Ranas, translated into English by Dana and illustrated by Frasconi. Topics include discussion of how many colors the book will be printed in, color saturation of the pages, how the book should be bound, the need to increase Spanish-language and bilingual collections in libraries, and the beginning of conversation about the next Mistral book the team planned, The Elephant and his Secret. The file includes a xerox of one of the mock ups for the book. Much of the correspondence regards marketing: McElderry submitted the title for the American Library Association's Mildred Batchelder Award for most outstanding translation of a children's book, Dana and Frasconi arranged to exhibit the original artwork at Brentano's Bookstore in Manhasset, NY and stage a dramatic performance there on November 16, 1972, and Dana read the book aloud on WBAI's children's storytelling program. McElderry also sent the book to institutions such as the Council for Interracial Books for Children, and La Casa del Libro in Puerto Rico. The file includes reviews and letters of reaction from booksellers and friends. It also includes correspondence related to Dana's other work, including her April 1972 recognition by the American Center of PEN for other translations of Mistral, and a talk she gave at the Israel-Ibero American Institute in 1973. Additionally, there is correspondence related to the braille edition of the title published by Howe Press of Perkins School for the Blind.
  - The Elephant and His Secret, 1974
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, her secretary Florence Sczesny, Dana, Dana's agent Joan Daves, and Frasconi regarding this bilingual expansion of Gabriela Mistral's story El Elefante Y Su Secreto, adapted by Dana and illustrated by Frasconi. Topics include discussion of Dana's expansion of the story and her translation of the expanded parts back into Spanish, and whether she should be credited as translator or author. There is also correspondence between McEdlerry and Pura Belpre White, a librarian at the New York Public Library, whom McElderry asked to read Dana's manuscript for regionalism in the Spanish; the file includes a typescript of the book annotated by White. Correspondence with Fransconi includes discussion of Frasconi's complicated relationship with Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, and of the book's color and design. As with Crickets and Frogs, there is much discussion of marketing, including which bookstores the book should be placed in, McElderry's hope that Daves will shop the rights to England, Germany and Brazil, and the excitement created by the book. Chatto & Windus was initially interested in the English rights, and McElderry's correspondence with editor Jane Birkett also includes discussion of Penelope Farmer's work; Editora Gaviota of Brazil took Portuguese-language rights. Additionally, there is discussion of the Book's selection as an American Library Association Notable Book for 1974, its inclusion in the 1975 Margaret Scoggin Memorial Collections of IBBY (a collection of excellent books sent to places where the publishing market is not fully developed), and its consideration for American Library Association's Margaret Batchelder Award for books in translation. McElderry corresponds with Della Thomas of the ALA about whether the book can really be considered a translation, but she is unable to get in touch with Dana and it seems that after March 1975, McElderry and Dana were never again in contact. Correspondence also includes letters from various publishers, librarians and academics interested in bilingual publishing and in Frasconi's artwork. Though McElderry had high hopes for the book it never sold as well as she projected and went out of print in 1984.
- Ruth Goldsmith
  - Phoebe Takes Charge
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Goldsmith and Paula Schwartz, regarding this novel about a girl who is left in charge of the house while her father is away. Topics include general changes and line edits from Schwartz, discussion about the jacket by Elise Primavera, interest from a publisher in South Africa, and McElderry's expression of continued interest in Goldsmith's work.
- John S. Goodall, 1976
  - Before the War: An Autobiography in Pictures
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, executive editor Judy Long, Goodall and Richard Garnett at Macmillan London regarding this pictorial autobiography of Goodall's life from birth to his enlistment in World War II. The correspondents sometimes use "Before I Was Thirty-One" as a working title. Like An Edwardian Summer, the book began as a gift for Goodall's wife. Topics of correspondence include how many copies of the book Atheneum will take from Macmillan, pricing, the book's title, differences between the British and American editions, how to handle a budget overage, interest in Japanese rights from the Japan Uni Agency and McEdlerry's frustrations with Garnett, whom she called "eccentric" (3 February 1981). The file also includes discussion of how to cover up a racist Hitchy Koo doll in one of Goodall's illustrations. Many other Goodall projects are discussed, including An Edwardian Season, Edwardian Entertainments, Victorians Abroad, John S. Goodall's Theatre: Sleeping Beauty, Shrewbettina and Paddy Pork pop up books, and a proposed project called "The Story of Emily" or "The Red House." McElderry, Goodall and Garnett also discuss the UK's political and economic troubles of 1981 and how they might affect the publishing industry. The book went out of print in 1986.
  - An Edwardian Christmas
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Goodall and Macmillan London's Richard Garnett discussing this sequal to An Edwardian Summer. Topics include McElderry's suggestion that the volume depict winter and not just Christmas, discussion of when Goodall's busy schedule would permit him to work on the paintings, and the enthusiastic reception of An Edwardian Summer in England. Goodall and McElderry also discuss Goodall's work on Story of An English Village and what would eventually become Goodall's Theatre: The Sleeping Beauty. File contains a black and white xerox of the entire volume. McElderry also corresponds with Goodall about the illness of Macmillan employee A.D. Maclean's son and the election of Jimmy Carter.
  - An Edwardian Summer, 1976
    Correspondence between McElderry, secretaries Barbara Douglas and Judy Long, Goodall, and Macmillan London staff Marni Hodgkin, A.D. Maclean, and Richard Garnett about this book of paintings depicting a day in the life of two boys during King Edward's reign. The project began as a gift for Goodall's wife Margaret and became the first in a series of pictorial works about life in England at the turn of the 20th century. Correspondence topics include how to market the book for both adults and children, whether there should be text to accompany the pictures and who should write it (Harold Macmillan eventually wrote a short foreward), size and design of the book, whether to print in Hong Kong or in England, how to insure the quality of the printing and McElderry's disappointment with the printer's initial work, slight differences in layout between UK and US editions, and McElderry's April 1976 visit to the UK. There are also letters between Marvin S. Brown, executive vice president of Atheneum, and Theresa Sacco, director at Macmillan, discussing disagreements between the firms about payment schedules for this book and future projects. Initially, McElderry had hoped that Artemis Verlag of Switzerland would join the printing run with Macmillan and Atheneum, and the file contains correspondence with Bruno Mariacher regarding his decision not to take the book due to its lack of text; a Dutch version was printed at the same time as the US and UK editions. The file also includes xeroxed mockups of the volume's cover and a draft of Macmillan's foreward edited by McElderry. Other projects of Goodall's discussed include Creepy Castle, Naughty Nancy, Surprise Picnic and Paddy Pork's Holiday; McElderry also discusses N.M. Bodecker's It's Raining Said John Twaining and Irene Haas's The Maggie B. McElderry writes to Goodall about his artwork for the 1976 Children's Book Council Book Week and the committee's request for Goodall to change the skin color of the little boy in his illustration. Correspondence also includes personal notes from friends to McElderry congratulating her on the volume, letters expressing interest from film studio Weston Woods and pulishers in Israel, and a letter from Gunars Mencis of The Bradford Exchange, expressing interest in using Goodall's work for their collector's plates.
  - An Edwardian Season
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Judy Long, Goodall, and Richard Garnett of Macmillan London about this book of paintings depicting the "season," that is the "period of three months... when aristocracy and wealthy classes converged on London to be near the Court" during the reign of King Edward (from volume's historical "Note"). Topics include whether or not Atheneum will be included in Macmillan's initial printing run, whether to print in Hong Kong or in England, delay of American release from Spring to Fall of 1980, and the shipment of preview copies twice being lost in the mail. There are also letters between McElderry and Michael Wace at Macmillan concerning the firms' ongoing disagreement about payment schedules. Many of Goodall's other titles are discussed, including Edwardian Summer, Paddy's New Hat, Paddy Pork's Holiday, Goodall's Theatre: The Sleeping Beauty, Story of an English Village, Lavinia's Cottage, Victorians Abroad, and Surprise Picnic. McElderry, Goodall and representatives from Macmillan also discuss a number of ideas for new books by Goodall, including Edwardian Entertainments, a Paddy Pork pop-up book, a project called "Escapade," which McElderry decided not to publish, and what would eventually become Before the War, here referred to as "Before I was Thirty-One." Additionally, there are letters of introduction between McElderry and Felicity Trotman, who became director of children's books at Macmillan in February, 1980, and some discussion of Atheneum's purchase by Scribner's. In a June 15, 1979 letter to Goodall, McElderry confirms the correct pronunciation of her last name.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1977-1980
    Three pieces of miscellaneous correspondence related to Goodall's Creepy Castle and An Edwardian Holiday.
- Kathryn Osebold Galbraith
  - Spots are Special!
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Galbraith and illustrator Diane Dawson (later Hearn) regarding Galbraith's first book, a picture book about the imaginative play of a girl with chicken pox. Early correspondence includes conversation with Christine Littman of the Donnell Library, whom McElderry asked to review the manuscript. Before settling on Dawson as the illustrator, McElderry and Galbraith also discussed using Jim Arnosky, Brinton Turkle, and Troy Howell (the file includes samples of his work). Correspondence between McElderry and Dawson centers around jacket design and Dawson's dissatisfaction with her own work; there are also several letters regarding Dawson's application to the Community Club of St. Bartholomew's Church on 50th St. in Manhattan. Other general topics include shopping the book to English publishers, interest from Parabel Verlag in Zurich, and the paperback book club edition of the title published by Xerox. McElderry and Galbraith also discuss other projects of Galbraith's, including Katie Did! and Come Spring, both published later by Atheneum, as well as Galbraith's concern over the sales figures for Spots are Special!
- Suzanne Haldane and Tom Hyman
  - [Untitled] Statue of Liberty Book
    General note
    One copy of "Statue of Liberty" by Charles Mercer (Putnam, 1979) removed from file. Paper bookmarks that remain with cover letter of July 1, 1979 removed: "Caption does not mention ex. pres. U.S. Grant visiting" from pg. 42; "Caption does not mention Bartholdi" from pg. 44.
    Correspondence between McElderry, Judy Long as executive editor, and Haldane regarding this proposed photo book about the design and building of the Statue of Liberty. The file includes letters with Haldane's idea for the book, photocopies of photographs she hoped to use, sample text by Tom Hyman, an unsigned contract and a specifications sheet listing expected size, number of pages, number of photographs, etc. The file also includes a letter to Marion Bell of Scribner Book Store soliciting an opinion on how such a book would compare with others on the market. The book was never published.
- Irina Hale, 1983
  - Brown Bear in a Brown Chair
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Hale, Hale's agent Laura Cecil, and Felicity Trotman of Macmillan London, regarding this picture book about a teddy bear who asks his owner to make him some clothes. The file includes several typescripts with McElderry's pencilled-in notes, a photocopy of Hale's initial dummy, photocopies of the cover art, five color slides of finished artwork, and copy of finalized jacket. Topics of correspondence include sizing of Hale's artwork to ensure accurate printing, whether the pages should have a color border, which typeface to use, whether the book will be printed by South China Printing Co. or in England, how McElderry and Trotman will commuicate effectively with each other and Hale, and artwork from the book being included in the 18th Exhibition of International Children's Picture Books put on by Shiko-Sha Co. in Japan. The correspondents also discuss Hale's other titles, Donkey's Dreadful Day and Chocolate Mouse and Sugar Pig, as well as author Nicki Daly and John S. Goodall's Above and Below Stairs, Story of an English Village and Paddy Goes Traveling. McElderry and Trotman discuss a large anti-nuclear rally in New York City and the Falkland's War.
  - Chocolate Mouse and Sugar Pig, And How They Ran Away to Escape Being Eaten
    Folder contains primarily business correspondence with/regarding the following individuals: Irina Hale (author/illustrator), Laura Cecil (her agent in the UK), Marni Hodgkin and Diane Denney (MacMillan London) and Hiroshi Imamura (Kaisei-Sha Publishers). The book had both US and UK editions, and was co-printed with Kaisei-Sha of Japan. Correspondence includes several versions of the full text, xeroxes of the illustrations, conversations about edits to both story and pictures, discussion of printing costs, variances between English and American spelling and punctuation, McElderry's meeting with Irina Hale at the Bologna Book Fair, discussion of future projects (Donkey and Brown Bear), trouble finding distributors for the book, anxiety over a delay in receiving films and copies of the work from England, early reviews of the work, and a remainder notice from 1983. Correspondence between McElderry and Cecil also references Harold Jones's There And Back Again and other Bunby books, Niki Daly's Vim the Rag Mouse, Edward Ardizzone's Hans Anderson, and authors Alec Lea and Simon Watson. Correspondence between McElderry and the team at MacMillan London also references John Goodall's An English Village, Ballooning Adventures of Paddy Pork and Creepy Castle, Joan Phipson's When the City Stopped, and Sylvia Fair's The Bedspread.
  - Donkey's Dreadful Day
- Lorraine Hare, 1983
  - Who Needs Her?